Guide to the Wilfred Thomason Grenfell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- WRITINGS, 1888-1940, undated; Series V; 3 linear feet (7 boxes)
  Articles and Essays includes a wide selection of Grenfell's magazine and newspaper articles and letters to the editor. The majority are semi-autobiographical and deal with Grenfell's conversion to active Christianity and with his subsequent work in Labrador. Other frequent topics include world politics and man's need for faith.
  This section is arranged in chronological order, followed by undated works arranged alphabetically by title. Both works in draft form and printed copies are included in this section.
  Pamphlets and Leaflets consists of a small number of works, almost all of which Grenfell wrote for the Grenfell Association. In most of these Grenfell merges autobiography with the history of the association. Also present is Grenfell's "catechism" for Labrador school children written to promote personal hygiene. The section is arranged chronologically.
  Reports, also in chronological order, consists of a few descriptions of ship wrecks and administrative reports for the RNMDSF and the Grenfell Association.
  notes, arranged chronologically, consists of informal jottings on varied subjects, many of which may have been made in preparation for one or more books or article.
  Other includes Grenfell's poems and reviews as well as a set of directions for the administration of the Grenfell Association after his death. This series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Books
    - Labrador: the Country and the People: partial draft, [pre-1909] (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - A Labrador Doctor, [pre-1919]
      - Draft outline (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Draft, chapters 4-7, 9-10 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Draft, chapters 14-16, 20-21, 23, 26 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Later draft, preface and chapters 1-6 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Later draft, chapters 7-14 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Later draft, chapters 15-22 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Later draft, chapters 23-28 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - "Autobiographical notes not used" (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Yourself and Your Body: draft, [pre-1924] (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - [Labrador Looks at the Orient], [post-1925]
      - [Draft of chapter 13?] (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - [Draft of chapter on India?] (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - The Fishermen's Saint: draft, 1930 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - The Romance of Labrador, [pre-1934]
      - Draft; table of contents, prologue, acknowledgment, foreward (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - Chapters 1-2; chapter 3, 3 drafts; chapter 4, 2 drafts; chapter 5, 2 drafts (Box 18, Folder 15)
      - Chapter 6, 2 drafts; chapter 7, 2 drafts; chapter 8 (Box 18, Folder 16)
      - Chapter 9, 2 drafts; chapter 10, 2 drafts; chapter 11 (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - Chapter 12, 3 drafts; chapter 13 (Box 18, Folder 18)
      - Chapter 14, 3 drafts; chapter 15, 2 drafts (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - "A Guide to Labrador": draft, undated (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - [Autobiographical fragment]: three drafts, undated (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - "Chapter II": holograph draft, undated (Box 18, Folder 22)
    - "Chapter VII": holograph draft, undated (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - Articles and Essays
    - 1888 May-1916 May (Box 19, Folder 24-116)
    - 1916 November-[post-1931?] (Box 20, Folder 117-198)
    - 1932 February-[1940?], undated (Box 21, Folder 199-285)
    - undated (Box 22, Folder 286-330)
  - Pamphlets and Leaflets
    - [1897?]-[1938], undated (Box 22, Folder 331-346)
  - Reports
    - 1902 November 19-[1922 July 23?], undated (Box 23, Folder 347-351)
  - Notes
    - [ca. 1890-1900]-1940 July 9, undated (Box 23, Folder 352-406)
  - Other
    - 1916 August-1938 April 4 (Box 23, Folder 407-411)
- PUBLIC SPEAKING, 1915-1940, undated; Series VI; 0.5; (1 box)
  This series is composed of Grenfell's speeches on Labrador and his experiences there. The speeches are divided by type into two sections.
  Addresses is arranged chronologically.
  Radio Broadcasts is also arranged in chronological order.
  - Addresses
    - [1915?]-[1940?], undated (Box 24, Folder 1-22)
  - Radio Broadcasts
    - [ca. 1920-1930]-[1936 Jan?], undated (Box 24, Folder 23-39)
- LEGAL AND FINANCIAL PAPERS, 1882-1939, undated; Series VII; 0.25; (1 box)
  This small series contains legal papers and certificates, passports, and financial papers such as invoices and receipts. Each type is arranged chronologically.
  - Legal papers and certificates, 1882-1905 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    General note
    See also: box 69, folder 1
  - Legal papers and certificates, 1907-1939, undated (Box 25, Folder 2-4)
  - Passports, 1922, 1924 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Financial papers, 1890-1938, undated (Box 25, Folder 6)
- ANNE (MACCLANAHAN) GRENFELL PAPERS, 1898-1938, undated; Series VIII; 2.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
  The papers of Anne Elizabeth Caldwell (MacClanahan) Grenfell have been collected into a separate series in recognition of the important role she played in the administration of the Grenfell Association (W.T. Grenfell referred to her as "the business brain"). It is unfortunate that only such a small amount of material is available here.
  The series is divided into Correspondence, Travel Diaries, Writings and Public Speaking, and Legal and Financial Papers.
  Correspondence comprises the majority of this series, and more than three quarters of the letters date from 1930-1938. Most of the correspondence concerns Grenfell Association business, though some personal letters, especially from Rosamond A. (Hill) MacClanahan, her mother, are included.
  This series is divided into outgoing, arranged chronologically, and incoming, arranged alphabetically by author. Letters from especially noted individuals and major correspondents (10 or more items) are foldered separately by author and placed at the end of the appropriate letter of the alphabet.
  Travel Diaries, arranged chronologically, consists of diaries from a world tour in 1924-1925 and an English tour in 1926.
  Writings and Public Speaking contains only the texts of one article and one radio broadcast.
  Legal and Financial Papers contains a small quantity of material arranged in chronological order.
  Additional papers of A.E. Grenfell are scattered through other series. See Series I for all of A.E. Grenfell's letters to and from W.T. Grenfell. See also papers in Series IX, X, and XII.
  - Correspondence
    - Outgoing, 1898-1938 June (Box 26, Folder 1-38)
    - Outgoing, 1938 July-Dec, undated (Box 27, Folder 39-60)
    - Incoming
      - Ab-Ash (Box 27, Folder 61)
      - Ashdown, Cecil S.(*), 1938 April 12-November 16 (Box 27, Folder 62)
      - Bad-Bu (Box 27, Folder 63-66)
      - Bieler, Katharine(*), 1938 February 18-November 15 (Box 27, Folder 67)
      - Ca-Cushi (Box 27, Folder 68-70)
      - Cushman, Eleanor(*), 1927, 1938 April-November (Box 27, Folder 71-73)
      - D (Box 28, Folder 74)
      - E (Box 28, Folder 75)
      - Fa-For (Box 28, Folder 76-77)
      - Ford, Clara B. (Mrs. Henry), undated (Box 28, Folder 78)
      - Ge-Gro (Box 28, Folder 79-80)
      - Graham, Ethel(*), 1938 March-September (Box 28, Folder 81)
      - Grenfell, Algernon G., 1923 (Box 28, Folder 82)
      - Grenfell, Frances-Grenfell, Lola, 1920, [1938?] (Box 28, Folder 83)
      - Grenfell, Wilfred T., Jr.(*), [ca. 1921-1924]-1934 (Box 28, Folder 84-85)
      - Grenfell Association-Grenfell Labrador Medical Mission, undated (Box 28, Folder 86)
      - Grey, Albert Henry George Grey, 4th Earl, 1911 (Box 28, Folder 87)
      - Hall-Hy (Box 28, Folder 88-89)
      - Hall, Louie(*), [1936?]-1938 November (Box 28, Folder 90-91)
      - Harris, Sir Charles A., 1920, 1922 (Box 28, Folder 92)
      - I (Box 28, Folder 93)
      - J (Box 28, Folder 94)
      - Kee-Kl (Box 28, Folder 95)
      - Keddie, Kitty (Witson)(*), 1938 (Box 28, Folder 96)
      - La-Lu (Box 28, Folder 97-99)
      - MacA-Mu (Box 28, Folder 100-102)
      - MacClanahan, Mrs. E.B.(*), [ca. 1923]-[1929?] Nov, undated (Box 28, Folder 103-106)
      - N (Box 28, Folder 107)
      - O (Box 28, Folder 108)
      - Pa-Pr (Box 28, Folder 109-110)
      - Q (Box 28, Folder 111)
      - Ra-Ru (Box 28, Folder 112-113)
      - Sai-Sch (Box 28, Folder 114-115)
      - Sco-Sy (Box 29, Folder 116-120)
      - Schweitzer, Helene Bresslau (Mrs. Albert), 1934, 1938 (Box 29, Folder 121)
      - Shnyder, F.E.(*), 1938 (Box 29, Folder 122-123)
      - Smith, Shirley S.(*), 1938 (Box 29, Folder 124-125)
      - Spalding, Katie(*), [1927-1928?], 1937-1938, [1938?] (Box 29, Folder 126-127)
      - Ta-Tu (Box 29, Folder 128-129)
      - Van Santvoord (Box 29, Folder 130)
      - Wak-Wo (Box 29, Folder 131-136)
      - Youell-Young (Box 29, Folder 137-138)
      - Unidentified (Box 29, Folder 139)
  - Travel Diaries
    - Diary: World trip, 1924 November 25-1925 March 30 (Box 29, Folder 140)
    - Diary: "Lecture Tour in England", 1926 (Box 29, Folder 141)
  - Writings and Public Speaking
    - "Letter from Lady Grenfell," reprinted from Among the Deep Sea Fisheries, 1938 October (Box 29, Folder 142)
    - Radio broadcast: typescript, 1932 (Box 29, Folder 143)
  - Legal and Financial Papers
    - Financial, 1909-1932 (Box 29, Folder 144)
- R.N.M.D.S.F. (ROYAL NATIONAL MISSION TO DEEP SEA FISHERMEN), 1893-1913, undated; Series IX; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  This series contains a small amount of correspondence and other papers from the RNMDSF, a British charitable organization devoted to the welfare of British sailors of the North Sea and Grand Banks fleets. W. T. Grenfell was affiliated with the organization from 1887-1912.
  Correspondence contains both incoming and outgoing letters of mission officials, particularly those attached to the St. John's, Newfoundland, office. (All of W. T. Grenfell's correspondence to, from, and about the RNMDSF is filed in Series I.)
  The remaining material, arranged chronologically by type, includes minutes of meetings, administration reports, financial papers, subject files on various mission projects, and a miscellany of leaflets.
  - Correspondence
    - Outgoing
      - 1904-1913 (Box 30, Folder 1-38)
    - Incoming
      - A-R (Box 31, Folder 39-46)
      - Sc-Str (Box 31, Folder 47)
      - Stirling, William R.(*), 1912-1913 (Box 31, Folder 48-49)
      - T-V (Box 31, Folder 50)
      - Wa-Woods (Box 31, Folder 51-52)
      - Wood, Francis H.(*), 1912-1913 (Box 31, Folder 53-54)
  - Minutes
    - 1893-1912, undated (Box 31, Folder 55)
  - Reports
    - 1893-1913 (Box 31, Folder 56)
  - Financial
    - Invoices and receipts, 1907-1912 (Box 31, Folder 57)
    - Statements of operating costs, St. Anthony, 1910 (Box 31, Folder 58)
    - General and special funds, 1912-1913 (Box 31, Folder 59)
    - Miscellaneous, 1896-1913, n.d (Box 31, Folder 60)
  - King George V Seamen's Institute
    - House Committee minutes, etc., 1912-1913 (Box 31, Folder 61)
    - Assorted minutes and memoranda, 1912-1913 (Box 31, Folder 62)
    - Papers re prosecution of Charles F. Karnopp, 1912-1913 (Box 31, Folder 63)
    - Donations and subscriptions, 1912 (Box 31, Folder 64)
    - Financial, 1912-1913 (Box 31, Folder 65-66)
    - Programs, 1910-1913, undated (Box 31, Folder 67)
    - Miscellaneous, 1912-1913, undated (Box 31, Folder 68)
  - Other
    - Papers re St. Anthony Orphanage, 1908-1910 (Box 31, Folder 69)
    - Supply lists and orders, 1910-1912 (Box 31, Folder 70)
    - Papers re mission ships, 1912-1913, undated (Box 31, Folder 71)
    - Pamphlets, leaflets, etc., 1897, undated (Box 31, Folder 72)
    - Miscellaneous, 1899-1913, undated (Box 31, Folder 73)
- GRENFELL ASSOCIATIONS, 1896-1949, undated; Series X; 0.5; (1 box)
  This small series contains scattered correspondence and other papers of workers at several branches of the International Grenfell Association. Correspondence is arranged chronologically. (All letters between W. T. Grenfell and Grenfell Associations are in Series I, those to or from A. E. Grenfell in Series VIII, and those to or from other Grenfell family members in Series XII.) The remaining material, arranged chronologically by type, includes minutes, reports, financial papers, subject files, and miscellaneous papers. Researchers interested in the work of the Grenfell Associations should also consult the New England Grenfell Association Papers, Ms Group #1200.
  - Correspondence
    - 1897-1953, undated (Box 32, Folder 1-5)
  - Minutes
    - 1913-1938, undated (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Reports
    - 1908-1944 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Financial
    - 1906-1939, undated (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Other
    - Co-operatives, 1896-1915, undated (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Lists of employees and volunteers, 1914-1938, undated (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Pamphlets, leaflets, etc., 1907-1949, undated (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1907-1934, undated (Box 32, Folder 12)
- THIRD PARTY, 1812-1978, undated; Series XI; 2.50 linear feet (4 boxes)
  THIRD PARTY contains miscellaneous correspondence, writings, and speeches generated by persons other than W. T. Grenfell, his family, or officials of the RNMDSF or the Grenfell Association. The series is divided into three sections, Correspondence, Writings, and Public Speaking.
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Included is a large group of letters in praise of Grenfell which were solicited by Dr. Clarence J. Blake in 1915 to counter adverse publicity about the Grenfell Association.
  Writings is divided into books, articles and essays, pamphlets and leaflets, reports, poems, and other, with each subsection being arranged chronologically. The material preserved here appears to be that which Grenfell kept as his reference files and includes writings about him.
  Public Speaking is arranged chronologically. It contains addresses made in honor of W. T. Grenfell, or for special occasions such as the opening of the new hospital in St. Anthony, Newfoundland.
  - Correspondence
    - 1893-1983, undated (Box 33, Folder 1-11)
  - Writings
    - Books
      - Our Kin. Genealogical Sketches, Pedigrees, and Arms of Sundry Families, by William Collings Lukis de Guerin; annotations by Wilfred Grenfell, 1890 (Box 33, Folder 12)
      - Livre de Prières du Soldat Français, anonymous, [1916?] (Box 33, Folder 13)
      - Tourists' Guide to China, compiled by California Directory Association, [ca. 1924-1925] (Box 33, Folder 14)
      - Chinese Farmer's Almanac, anonymous, 1925 (Box 33, Folder 15)
      - The King's Book, by John Drinkwater, et al., 1935 May (Box 33, Folder 16)
      - La Cooperation, by H.H. Hannam, 1939 January (Box 33, Folder 17)
      - Pictures of Indian Life and Characters, anonymous, undated (Box 33, Folder 18)
    - Articles and Essays
      - [1812]-1944 January (Box 34, Folder 19-118)
      - [1949]-1983, undated (Box 35, Folder 119-160a)
    - Pamphlets and Leaflets
      - 1840-[post-1965], undated (Box 35, Folder 161-187)
    - Reports
      - 1906-[1939?] (Box 35, Folder 188-196)
    - Poems
      - 1886-1934, undated (Box 36, Folder 197-209)
    - Other
      - 1769-1965, undated (Box 36, Folder 210-224)
    - Public Speaking
      - 1907-1977, undated (Box 36, Folder 225-237)
- FAMILY PAPERS, 1849-1978, undated; Series XII; 0.25; (1 box)
  This series contains papers relating to the families of W. T. Grenfell and his wife A. E. M. Grenfell. There are two sections, Grenfell Family and MacClanahan Family.
  Grenfell Family is composed of a small group of papers from W. T.Grenfell's parents, siblings, and children. It includes correspondence (arranged chronologically) comprised mostly of letters of condolence on W. T. Grenfell's death and letters about W. T. Grenfell, Jr.'s proposed biography of W. T. Grenfell. Other papers such as an autobiographical fragment by Jane Georgiana (Hutchinson) Grenfell, mother of W. T. Grenfell, are also filed here.
  MacClanahan Family contains a small amount of correspondence from the family of A.E.M. Grenfell, and from the family of her mother, Rosamond A. (Hill) MacClanahan, arranged in chronological order, and some miscellaneous items such as Rosamond (Hill) MacClanahan's normal school certificate.
  - Grenfell Family
    - Correspondence, 1881-1981, undated (Box 37, Folder 1-11)
    - Writings, 1920-1978, undated (Box 37, Folder 12-15b)
    - Legal papers, 1883-1912 (Box 37, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1880-1940, undated (Box 37, Folder 17)
  - MacClanahan Family
    - Correspondence, 1856-1926, undated (Box 37, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous, 1849-1873 (Box 37, Folder 19)
- MEMORABILIA, 1855-1970, undated; Series XIII; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  MEMORABILIA is divided into four sections: Scrapbooks, Newspaper Clippings, Maps and Drawings, and Other.
  Scrapbooks includes 21 chronologically arranged volumes of correspondence, newspaper clippings, certificates, and other memorabilia compiled by Grenfell and his family. In 1979 these fragile volumes were preserved on four reels of microfilm. Correspondence and important documents were then removed and filed in the appropriate series, and the original scrapbooks were destroyed. The researcher interested in seeing the scrapbooks should consult HM 80, Series I, Reels 1-4.
  Newspaper Clippings is arranged chronologically. Most of the contents concern Grenfell and/or Labrador.
  Maps and Drawings contains works by W.T. Grenfell and by others.
  Other includes a tape-recorded interview with Wilfred Mesher, who worked with Grenfell; programs; announcements of lectures; printed invitations; and timetables, as well as other miscellaneous items.
  - Scrapbooks (Box 1–4)
    See: Volumes 1-21, 1893-1939
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - 1892-1984, undated (Box 38, Folder 1-5)
  - Maps and Drawings
    - "Charts and Sketches" by Wilfred T. Grenfell, [1896-1931] (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Maps and charts drawn by Wilfred T. Grenfell, 1908-1921, undated (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - Maps and charts, undated (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - Notebook with drawings by Wilfred T. Grenfell, [ca. 1910-1920] (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - Drawings by Wilfred T. Grenfell, 1909-1937, undated (Box 39, Folder 10-11)
    - Drawings, undated (Box 39, Folder 12)
      See also: box 69, folder 2
  - Other
    - Cassette tape-recording, "Interview with Wilfred Mesher, Number 1", 1971 (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - Programs, 1893-1941, undated (Box 40, Folder 14-15)
    - Announcements, 1907-1938, undated (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - Invitations, 1905-1940, undated (Box 40, Folder 17)
    - Tickets, calling cards, etc., 1910-1937, undated (Box 40, Folder 18)
    - Schedules, timetables, etc., 1908-1925, undated (Box 40, Folder 19)
    - Membership lists, passenger lists, etc., 1907-1939, undated (Box 40, Folder 20)
    - Menus, 1907-1934 (Box 40, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous, 1855-1934, undated (Box 40, Folder 22)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1855-1958, undated; Series XIV; 11.50 linear feet (28 boxes)
  Almost 10,500 photographs, mostly of Labrador and Newfoundland, have been arranged by location or by subject in this series. They provide a pictorial history from 1890-1940 of many Newfoundland and Labrador towns and a graphic portrayal of the economic hardship of the region. There is also a record of W.T. Grenfell and his family throughout their lives and a survey of his friends and associates.
  The photographs were originally mounted in albums, but they have now been removed and placed in envelopes. Each photograph and envelope bears a number such as 1-1-60, i.e. box 1, folder 1, photograph 60. All annotations from the albums have been copied onto the envelopes and keyed to the photographs by the numbers written on them. A large number of photographs had no annotation, and tentative identifications, indicated by square brackets, have been made wherever possible. Several albums could not be dismantled. Photographs in these albums were photocopied and the copies then filed in the appropriate sections. Because these albums are in poor condition they may only be used after the copies have been consulted.
  Mission Stations contains photographs of locations in Newfoundland and Labrador where the Grenfell Association has hospitals, schools, or other facilities. The photographs are arranged alphabetically by place name and then chronologically. Whenever there are many photographs for one location, they have been further divided by topic, for instance "Hospital" or "Liv'eres" (the year-round residents of Newfoundland and Labrador). Within each topic photographs are chronologically arranged. Many of the Collateral Families contains photographs of other family members, arranged chronologically by family.
  MacClanahan Family contains photographs of the family of A. E. M. Grenfell and of their residences, arranged chronologically within each folder.
  Staff and Acquaintances contains pictures of many of the people represented in the correspondence, including such notables as Henry Ford and Albert Schweitzer. The section is arranged alphabetically by name, and chronologically for each person. Unidentified photographs are grouped in chronological order at the end.
  Grenfell Association includes photographs of the Dog Team Tavern and association activities and projects, arranged chronologically within each folder.
  RNMDSF includes a few pictures of mission activities, in chronological order.
  Scientific Projects contains photographs of projects W. T. Grenfell was involved in, notably the use of cellulose acetate in solaria. Each group is arranged chronologically.
  World Tours includes pictures from the Grenfells' travels, arranged chronologically. Pictures from earlier tours are more heavily annotated than later ones.
  Places Not in Newfoundland or Labrador contains photographs of a number of countries, especially Britain and the United States. The early photographs are heavily annotated.
  Moravian Stations contains photographs of missions in Labrador established by Moravian missionaries. They are arranged alphabetically by place name and then chronologically.
  Other Newfoundland and Labrador Sites contains photographs of places with neither Grenfell Association facilities nor Moravian missions. It is arranged parallel to Mission Stations, and ends with photographs of unidentified locations in chronological order.
  Labrador Survey consists of photographs taken by the Forbes-Grenfell North Labrador Expedition and is arranged by location roughly from north to south.
  "Liv'eres" consists of photographs of year-round residents of Labrador, including orphanage children. Many of the pre-1910 photographs are particularly striking. The section is arranged chronologically.
  Eskimos includes portraits of Eskimos, pictures of their homes, and of their daily life. Particularly interesting is a narrative sequence of daily life recorded by W. T. Grenfell in the winter of 1900-01. Each subject is arranged chronologically.
  Indians is arranged parallel to Eskimos. Agriculture and Livestock is arranged chronologically. The photographs are from unidentified locations.
  Hunting is arranged chronologically. It includes a narrative sequence of a seal hunt in 1892 in which W. T. Grenfell participated.
  Transportation is arranged chronologically within the following subsections: airplanes, dog sleds, motor vehicles, railroads, and reindeer. The final subsection, ships, is arranged alphabetically by ship and chronologically for each ship, with unidentified ships filed chronologically at the end.
  Icebergs is arranged chronologically.
  W. T. Grenfell contains a chronological record of W. T. Grenfell from 1873-1940, followed by a group of narrative sequences, in chronological order, dealing with various episodes in Grenfell's career.